<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Differential Geometry on Shiraz</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/differential-geometry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Differential Geometry on Shiraz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.2</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 12:46:04 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/differential-geometry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Differentials in Lie Theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lemmas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 12:46:04 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lemmas/</guid>
      <description>Some results about the differentials (i.e., pushforwards) of the exponential and logarithm maps of a Lie group. I rely extensively on the interpretation of tangent vectors as equivalence classes of curves.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integration on SO(3)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/so3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 11:27:55 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/so3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I will construct the Haar measure for $SO(3)$ and pull it back to the axis-angle parametrization of orthogonal matrices. The goal is to be able to integrate (and thereby define probability densities) on $SO(3)$.
My &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups_riemannian&#34; class=&#34;accented&#34;&gt;
    earlier post
&lt;/a&gt; on the Riemannian volume form is a prerequisite, though you could also just skip over any equations involving exterior calculus (distinguished by the use of the &amp;ldquo;$\wedge$&amp;rdquo; operation) and focus on the computations done in axis-angle coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Levi-Civita Connection</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 10:43:16 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sphere/</guid>
      <description>Here, I solve Problem 5-5 from John Lee&amp;rsquo;s book on &lt;em&gt;Riemannian Manifolds&lt;/em&gt;, which demonstrates the non-flatness of the 2-sphere. This problem is particularly interesting because it serves as the motivating example for a later chapter in the book on curvature.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lie Groups as Riemannian Manifolds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups_riemannian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 09:53:05 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups_riemannian/</guid>
      <description>A &lt;span class=accented&gt;Lie group&lt;/span&gt; is a group that is also a (continuous, differentiable) topological space. To measure lengths and volumes (and relatedly, to define and integrate probability densities) we need to endow the group with additional structure so that it is not merely a manifold, but a &lt;span class=accented&gt;Riemannian manifold&lt;/span&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lie Groups: Construction and Geometry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups_construction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 14:20:59 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups_construction/</guid>
      <description>There are multiple ways to construct new groups from old ones. I provide an intuition for how these constructions work, and also go over some of the additional structures that can be imposed on Lie groups, paving the path towards doing differential geometry and calculus on Lie groups.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lie Group-Lie Algebra Correspondence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 07:24:59 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lie-groups/</guid>
      <description>A &lt;span class=accented&gt;topological group&lt;/span&gt; is a set of elements that has both a group operation and a topology. The group operation satisfies the usual axioms (same as those of finite groups), and the presence of a topology lets us say things like &amp;rsquo;the group is connected&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the group operation is continuous&#39;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector Fields on Manifolds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vector-fields/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 11:22:28 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vector-fields/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I have struggled to pin down what the scope of my blog should be. There is plenty of exposition out there on just about every aspect of modern mathematics, but especially on &lt;span class=accented&gt;exterior calculus&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=accented&gt;differential geometry&lt;/span&gt; due to their situation at the intersection of several areas in theoretical and applied mathematics. So then what is the scope of my blog? Maybe it is for me to catalog the process of self-learning mathematics as an engineering major who lacks a curricular background in modern mathematics. Maybe it is to assure others like me (who are also privileged enough to learn mathematics in isolation of such material concerns as its &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;job prospects&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;) that it can be done. This post will do a bit of both; it serves in part the purpose of organizing my own thoughts on these matters, and in part the purpose of providing a roadmap for others who are interested in embarking on a similar journey.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
