<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Shiraz</title>
    <link>https://shirazkn.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Shiraz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2023 21:07:38 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://shirazkn.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cat Theory 😼</title>
      <link>https://shirazkn.github.io/posts/cat_theory_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2023 21:07:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shirazkn.github.io/posts/cat_theory_1/</guid>
      <description>One of my biggest motivations for starting a blog was Eugenia Cheng&amp;rsquo;s delightful book The Joy of Abstraction 1. It&amp;rsquo;s a surprisingly accessible, gentle introduction to category theory, a topic that is usually only taught to graduate students in math. She compiled part of the book using notes from the category theory class that she teaches at the Art Institute of Chicago, a testament to the aesthetic appreciation that one can expect to gain of category theory, irrespective of their academic background.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Quest for Completeness</title>
      <link>https://shirazkn.github.io/posts/language_and_logic2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 08:46:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shirazkn.github.io/posts/language_and_logic2/</guid>
      <description>In my earlier post I suggested that there is no objective notion of logical truth, that whether a statement is &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo; can depend on the system of truth that one is operating in. Here we will develop that argument further using the concept of axiomatic systems. This is a long one, but I&amp;rsquo;m excited to talk about it!
Axiomatic Systems An axiomatization is an assignment of rules (axioms) such as &amp;ldquo;one plus one equals two,&amp;rdquo; making up an axiomatic system or a formal system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misuse as a Use of Language</title>
      <link>https://shirazkn.github.io/posts/language_and_logic1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 13:48:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shirazkn.github.io/posts/language_and_logic1/</guid>
      <description>This post concerns the question of whether spoken and written languages like English could be &amp;rsquo;logical&amp;rsquo; by design, and why they aren&amp;rsquo;t. I will break this discussion up into two posts. The first one (this post) does not require a mathematical background whatsoever, whereas the second touches on the concepts of axioms, theorems and proofs. Both parts are somewhat self-contained, so you can skip to the next post if you&amp;rsquo;d like.</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
